

University of Stavanger (UiS), 4036 Stavanger, Norway



jassem.abbasi@gmail.com; jassem.abbasi@uis.no



CLICK HERE FOR MORE INFO









## ABOUT

A researcher with experience in working close with university and industry, professional in numerical analysis of physical processes, especially flow in porous media and three years of research in the field of Scientific Machine Learning, and Deep Learning.

# QUALIFICATIONS

**Programming** 

Reservoir Engineering/Simulation

Scientific Machine Learning / Deep Learning

Computational Fluid Dynamics (CFD)

Numerical/Analytical Simulation

Flow in Porous Media | Thermodynamics

**Data Analytics** 

Cloud/GPU Computing

# SKILLS

ECLIPSE, CMG, MRST (...)

COMSOL, OpenFoam

Petrel

PVTi, PVTsim (...)

PipeSim (...)



Python, C#, MATLAB

TensorFlow, PyTorch

Sklearn, SciPy, (...) PyTorch Geometric

Git (Version Control)

Azure ML

Databases (MySQL) **GPU** Computing

OOP (Object Oriented Programming)

**PowerBI** 

WP Web Development Adobe Photoshop **Digital Marketing** 



# LANGUAGES

**English** Fluent

**Norwegian** Elementary

**Persian** Native

# CURRENT ACTIVITY

Application of Physics-Informed Neural Networks in Core-Scale Simulation of Flow in Porous Media

We are focused on the Physics-Informed Neural Networks based analysis (forward and inverse) of flow in porous media at core scale processes, in specific 3D simulation of two-phase flow (CO2 flooding) in multi-scale fractured cores.

# EXPERIENCES (selected)

EQUINOR ASA, Norway (2022)

Subsurface Geoscience/Reservoir Simulation Engineer (Summer Intern)

ZODAN SOLUTIONS LTD., UK (2019-2020)

Scientific Software Developer

SHIRAZ UNIVERSITY/PETROAZMA OIL COMPANY, Iran (2016-2018)

Reservoir [Simulation] Engineer/Researcher

PETROTIRAZIS OIL COMPANY PTED., Iran (2016)

Scientific Software Developer (Intern)

# EDUCATION

ETH Zürich (Summer 2024)

ETH Al Center – Visiting Researcher

UNIVERSITY OF STAVANGER (2021- Sep. 2024)

Petroleum Technology – Scientific Machine Learning (PhD)

SHIRAZ UNIVERSITY (2014-2016)

Reservoir Engineering (M.Sc.)

PETROLEUM UNIVERSITY OF TECHNOLOGY (2010-2014)

Reservoir Engineering (B.Sc.)

# PUBLICATIONS (selected)

Ongoing: History Matching of Multi-Scale and Multi-Phase Flow in Fractured Porous Media Using Physics-Informed Neural Networks

SPE Journal (2024): Application of Physics-Informed Neural Networks for Estimation of Saturation Functions from Counter current Spontaneous Imbibition Tests →

Neurocomputing (2024): Physical Activation Functions (PAFs): An Approach for More Efficient Induction of Physics into Physics-Informed Neural Networks (PINNs) →

Energy and Fuels (2023): Simulation and Prediction of Spontaneous Imbibition at Early and Late Times Using Physics-Informed Neural Networks →

Petroleum Science (2021): On the Impact of Solutal Marangoni Convection during Chemical Flooding for Improved Oil Recovery →

Journal of Petroleum Sci. and Eng. (2018): A new numerical approach for investigation of the effects of dynamic capillary pressure in imbibition process  $\rightarrow$ 





# EXPERIENCES

## UNIVERSITY OF STAVANGER, Norway (2021-2024)

### PhD Research Fellow in Petroleum Technology/ Artificial Intelligence

Research on Physics Informed Neural Networks (PINNs) and its application in solving the forward and inverse problems of flow in porous media.

I am planning to embark on a visit to Brown University during the spring 2024, as a participant in a research collaboration involving researchers from the University of Stavanger, Brown University, and Stanford University.

### EQUINOR ASA, Norway (2022)

#### Subsurface Engineer | Reservoir Simulation (intern)

During this two-month internship, I worked on an interesting business/engineering case of related to tying-back of two offshore gas fields while both economical and engineering aspects of the project was needed to be considered. In this project, I could finish the numerical simulation of the investigating case and finally provide statistical business/engineer insights to the management team.

### ZODAN SOLUTIONS LTD., UK (2018-2021)

### Scientific Software Developer

Developing commercial software for simulation of thermodynamics of subsurface geofluids including oil, gas, and water

#### SHIRAZ UNIVERSITY/PETROAZMA OIL COMPANY (2016-2018)

#### Reservoir Simulation Engineer | Research Assistant

Pore to field scale study of EOR methods in several oil fields. Screening of EOR methods, experiment design and evaluation, upscaling, numerical and analytical simulation, geological analysis, pilot design and proposal preparation. Also, research assistant at academic research projects and advisor of several master students.

### PETROTIRAZIS OIL COMPANY PTED., Iran (2016)

#### Software Developer

Development of software related to petroleum industry. The software was used for providing fast-track development plan in the early stages of field development projects.





# HONORS & AWARDS

- 2024 Awarded a prestigious research commercialization fund (Qualification Project) from Research Council of Norway (~0.5 MNOK)
  - Pisces-Al: Physics-Informed Al for Subsurface Characterization Experiments
- 2024 Awarded as the **Best PhD Candidate** of The Year by **SPE Stavanger**
- 2024 Chair in two sessions at EAGE Annual Exhibition and Conference in Oslo
  - ML & Al for Geological Characterization I
  - ML & AI for Geological Characterization III
- 2023 Awarded an innovation research stipend (Funded by: Validé AS, Stavanger, Norway)
  - Development of a new generation of solvers for the interpretation of core-scale experiments
- 2019 Ranked 3rd in Second Iranian Petro Match (IPM)
  - Hackathon: optimization of well-placing in a highly heterogeneous oil field

### 2018-Present Journal and Conference Reviewer

- Journal of Petroleum Science and Engineering
- Journal of Computational Geosciences
- Journal of Neurocomputing
- Journal of Natural Gas Science and Engineering
- ACS Omega

- Journal of Geophysics and Engineering
- Journal of Molecular Liquids
- Journal of Petrophysics
- EAGE Conferences
- 2019 3 Years Distinguished Researcher of EOR Research Centre at Shiraz University
- 2017 Distinguished Researcher of EOR Research Centre at Shiraz University
- 2017 Winner of Military Service Exemption Award of Iran's National Elites Foundation
- 2010-2014 Ranked among the 1st 0.5% of participants in the National Entrance Exam for the Universities of Iran





Click on  $\bigcirc$  to download files

# JOURNAL ARTICLES

Application of Physics-Informed Neural Networks for Estimation of Saturation Functions from Countercurrent Spontaneous Imbibition Tests

SPE Journal (2023) – SPE-218402-PA Jassem Abbasi, Pål Østebø Andersen

Simulation and Prediction of Counter current Spontaneous Imbibition at Early and Late Times Using Physics-Informed Neural Networks

Energy and Fuels (2023) Jassem Abbasi, Pål Østebø Andersen

Physical Activation Functions (PAFs): An Approach for More Efficient Induction of Physics into Physics-Informed Neural Networks (PINNs)

Neural-Computing (2024) Jassem Abbasi, Pål Østebø Andersen

Theoretical Comparison of Two Setups for Capillary Pressure Measurement by Centrifuge Heliyon

Jassem Abbasi, Pål Østebø Andersen

A Novel Physics based Method for Modelling COVID-19

Harris Sajjad Rabbani, Kofi Osei-Bonsu, Jassem Abbasi, Peter Kwame Osei-Bonsu, Thomas Daniel Seers

A Multiscale Study on the Effects of Dynamic Capillary Pressure in Two-Phase Flow in Porous Media Korean Journal of Chemical Engineering, 2020 Jassem Abbasi, Mojtaba Ghaedi, Masoud Riazi

On the Impact of Solutal Marangoni Convection during Chemical Flooding for Improved Oil Recovery

Petroleum Science, 2020

Sepideh Palizdan, Jassem Abbasi, Masoud Riazi, Mohammadreza Malayeri

Prediction of multiphase critical choke flow behavior by using a rigorous artificial neural network method •

Journal of Flow Measurement and Instrumentation, 2019

Saeed Rashid, Ali Ghamartale, Jassem Abbasi, Hoda Darvish, Afshin Tatar

A new numerical approach for investigation of the effects of dynamic capillary pressure in imbibition process  $\bigcirc$ 

Journal of Petroleum Science and Engineering, 2018 Jassem Abbasi, Mojtaba Ghaedi, Masoud Riazi





# JOURNAL ARTICLES (cont.)

Improvements in scaling of counter-current imbibition recovery curves using a shape factor including permeability anisotropy

Journal of Geophysics and Engineering, 2018 Jassem Abbasi, Shiva Sarafrazi, Masoud Riazi, Mojtaba Ghaedi

Modified shape factor incorporating gravity effects for scaling counter-current imbibition Journal of Petroleum Science and Engineering, 2017
Jassem Abbasi, Masoud Riazi, Mojtaba Ghaedi, Abouzar Mirzaei-Paiaman

<u>Discussion on Similarity of Recovery Curves in Scaling of Imbibition Process in Fractured Porous</u>
Media

Journal of Natural Gas Science and Engineering, 2016 Jassem Abbasi, Mojtaba Ghaedi, Masoud Riazi

A Simulation investigation of Performance of Polymer Injection in Hydraulically Fractured Heterogeneous Reservoirs

Journal of Petroleum Exploration and Production Technology, 2016 Jassem Abbasi, Babak Raji, Masoud Riazi, Azim Kalantari Asl





# CONFERENCE ARTICLES

Application of Physics-Informed Neural Networks for Estimation of Saturation Functions from Countercurrent Spontaneous Imbibition Tests

EAGE IOR 2023, Netherland

Jassem Abbasi, Pål Østebø Andersen

Simulation and Prediction of Counter-current Spontaneous Imbibition at Early and Late Times Using Physics-Informed Neural Networks

SPE EUROPEC 2023, July, Vienna, Austria

Jassem Abbasi, Pål Østebø Andersen

Improved Initialization of Non-linear Solvers in Numerical Simulation of Flow in Porous Media with a Real-time Deep Learning Approach

SPE EUROPEC 2022, July, Madrid, Spain

Jassem Abbasi, Pål Østebø Andersen

Machine learning Assisted Study on Determination of the Most Relevant Parameters for Prediction of Permeability of Tight Sandstones in Mercury Injection Capillary Pressure Tests

SPWLA (SPE) Stavanger 2022, June, Stavanger, Norway

Jassem Abbasi, Jiuyu Zhao, Sameer Ahmed, Jianchao Cai, Pål Østebø Andersen

Theoretical Comparison of Two Setups for Capillary Pressure Measurement by Centrifuge EAGE IOR 2021, Online

lassem Abbasi, Pål Østebø Andersen

Pore Scale Direct Numerical Simulation of Simultaneous Marangoni-driven Convection and Mass Diffusion in a Chemical Flooding Process

82th EAGE Annual Conference & Exhibition 2020, Amsterdam

Jassem Abbasi, Sepideh Palizdan, Masoud Riazi, Mohammadreza Malayeri

Investigation of simultaneous co-current and counter-current spontaneous imbibition in presence of gravity effects

80th EAGE Annual Conference & Exhibition 2018

Jassem Abbasi, Mojtaba Ghaedi, Masoud Riazi, Saeed Rashid

A discussion About the Effect of Considering the Dynamic Capillary Forces on Dissimilarity of Imbibition Recovery Curves

**EAGE Saint Petersburg 2018** 

Jassem Abbasi, Mojtaba Ghaedi, Masoud Riazi





# CERTIFICATES



# **Machine Learning**

By Stanford University (hosted by Coursera)

In Progress



# **Physics-Informed Neural Networks (PINNs)**

By KTH and Brown universities

July 2023 - No Expiration Date



## **Fundamentals of Scalable Data Science**

By **IBM** (hosted by **Coursera**)

June 2020 - No Expiration Date



# **Fundamentals of Digital Marketing**

By Google

July 2020 - No Expiration Date



# OpenFOAM & Computational Fluid Dynamics (CFD)

By Shiraz University

April 2019 - No Expiration Date



## **Reservoir Simulation – ECLIPSE**

By Petroleum University of Technology

June 2015 - No Expiration Date





# TEACHING EXPERIENCES

### **Applied Reservoir Simulation**

University of Stavanger / University of Campinas, 2024 Teacher Assistant

## Advanced Fluid Phase Equilibrium Calculations (workshop)

Shiraz University, 2018 Lecturer

## Advanced MATLAB Programming Language (workshop)

Shiraz University, 2018 Lecturer

## **Reservoir Fluid Properties**

Shiraz University, 2017 Teacher Assistant

### **Reservoir Simulation**

Shiraz University, 2017 Teacher Assistant

## **ECLIPSE Reservoir Simulation Software**

Shiraz University, 2015-2017 Software Instructor

### PVTi and PVTsim Fluid Modelling Software

Shiraz University, 2016 Software Instructor

## PipeSim Production Engineering Software

Shiraz University, 2016 Software Instructor





# REFERENCES

### Pål Østebø Andersen

2020-Present, University of Stavanger Associate Professor; Pal.andersen@uis.no

#### Aksel Hiorth

2020-Present, University of Stavanger Professor; <a href="mailto:aksel.hiorth@uis.no">aksel.hiorth@uis.no</a>

### Farokh Shoaei

2022, Equinor, Norway Leader Reservoir Technology; <a href="mailto:ffk@equinor.com">ffk@equinor.com</a>

### Siddhartha Mishra

2024, ETH Zurich, Switzerland Professor in Applied Mathematics [Scientific Machine Learning]; siddhartha.mishra@sam.math.ethz.ch

#### Zohrab Dastkhan

2018-2020, Zodan Solutions (now: Qatar Petroleum)
Consultant Reservoir Engineer/Software Developer, London/Doha; zdastkhan@gmail.com

### Masoud Riazi

2014-2020, Shiraz University (now: Nazarbayev University) Associate Professor; masoud.riazi@nu.edu.kz